[Waco] New Hope Baptist Church records, Inclusive: 1875-1988, Bulk: 1922-1985
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] New Hope Baptist Church records
Inclusive: 1875-1988, Bulk: 1922-1985
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
662
New Hope Baptist Church, 1866 -
6 document boxes and 2 oversized boxes.
The [Waco] New Hope Baptist Church records consist of correspondence, legal, financial, and literary manuscripts generated by the church members, along with photographs and other printed materials.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Organized in 1866, New Hope Baptist Church is one of the oldest African-American churches in Waco, Texas. Noted throughout their history for their excellent church music programs, New Hope continues to work for God’s glory in the Waco African-American community today.
After the end of the American Civil War, emancipation came to the African-American people in the Waco community. Though the enslaved people of the area had been allowed limited worship opportunities at First Baptist Church of Waco, the newly liberated people of the community looked to form their own church. With new hope for the future, eighteen African-Americans from First Baptist Church created their own missionary Baptist church in 1866, with assistance from Baylor University President Rufus Burleson and First Baptist Pastor S.G. O’Bryan. The name “New Hope” was selected as the name for the new church, suggested by longtime resident Stephen Cobb.
The new church quickly became the most prestigious African-American church in Waco. Despite the church’s youth, New Hope outgrew their first church home, an old foundry building on the corner of Jefferson Avenue and Sixth Street, in one year. In partnership with a local Methodist church, New Hope built its first permanent church structure in 1867. That building did not last very long before it was destroyed to make way for a school. New Hope rented the school on Sunday mornings for services for several years until 1873, when they built a modest wooden church elsewhere. In 1884 under the leadership of the church’s seventh pastor, a large two-story brick church was built for the still-growing church. This served the church until the current church was built in 1923 at the corner of Sixth Street and Marlborough Avenue. The collection contains minutes chronicling the story of New Hope starting in 1875.
After Stephen Cobb, the most influential pastor of New Hope was Dr. J. Newton Jenkins, who served as pastor from 1907 until 1950. As the tenth pastor of New Hope, Jenkins is credited with raising enough money to pay off all debts in his first ninety days on the job. Jenkins and the church members also worked together to build the current church at Sixth and Marlborough. The eleventh pastor of New Hope, Dr. Marvin C. Griffin, pioneered a radio ministry, a citywide transportation system to the church on Sunday, and oversaw a proliferation of ministry groups within the church to do everything from training future church leaders to women’s ministry. The most recent pastor, Reginald D. Terry, began his ministry in 1986. Legal documents, minutes, financial papers, photographs, and many other printed materials detail New Hope’s building programs and other activities from this era.
From at least 1905, and probably before that, New Hope Baptist Church was noted for its music programs. First led by Dr. G.S. Conner, New Hope had at least forty people in their choir by 1905. In conjunction with students from Paul Quinn College, New Hope pioneered a musical program that had an adult choir, a children’s choir, and an orchestra. Notable members through the years were Jules Bledsoe, later an international African-American opera star, and Vivienne Malone-Mayes, one of the first African-Americans to receive advanced degrees in mathematics and the first African-American professor at Baylor University. In fact, Vivienne directed the youth choir of New Hope for fifteen years. The collection contains programs and photographs of the New Hope music ministry dating to the early 1900s, including a piano recital program for then fourteen year old Vivienne Malone Mayes.
Based in its rich heritage as one of the oldest African-American churches in the Waco area, New Hope Baptist Church continues to worship and minister at its historical 1920s church today.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] New Hope Baptist Church records begin in 1875 and ends in 1986. The Literary Productions series is by far the largest in the collection. An extensive group of church minutes gives the early history of the church from 1875 to 1927 with few breaks in between. An unusually large number of preserved musical programs and photographs of musical organizations within the church shows New Hope’s early interest in music as a part of worship. A large number of documents pertaining to the building of New Hope’s current church in the early 1920s are preserved within the collection.
Arrangement
The [Waco] New Hope Baptist Church records were organized prior to this finding aid, but with no inventory of the entire collection or finding aid. Many of the folder titles already existing were kept.
Currently, the collection is arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, III. Financial Documents, IV. Literary Productions, and V. Photographic Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 662. Acquired 1974-05-02
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Irene Cobb papers, Inclusive: 1886-1991, Bulk: 1960-1989
Frances Cobb Todd papers, Inclusive: 1899-1990, undated, Bulk:1960-1990
Smith-Cobb Family collection, Inclusive: 1861-1968, Bulk: 1948-1965
Marvin C. Griffin papers, Inclusive: 1940-2011, undated, Bulk: 1960-1999, undated
Vivienne Malone-Mayes papers, Inclusive: 1966-1977, undated; Bulk: 1973-1976
Frances Cobb Todd papers, Inclusive: 1899-1990, undated, Bulk:1960-1990
Related references
[Bicentennial Committee, Irene E. Cobb, Chairman]. History of New Hope Baptist Church, 1866-1976. 1976.
[Church Anniversary Committee]. The 114th Anniversary New Hope Baptist Church, 1866-1980. 1980.
Richardson, Diamond. "African-American Tradition, 145 Years Young." Focus, 2011 Fall.
"Waco Local News." Dallas Morning News, 1985 December 6.
Waco Regional Baptist Association, Accessed 2012 August 13.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
New Hope Baptist Church (Waco, Tex.).
Places
Texas -- Photographs.; Waco (Tex.) -- History.
Subjects
African American Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; African American churches -- Texas -- Waco.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; City churches -- Texas -- Waco.; Clergy -- Texas-- Waco.; Waco (Tex.) -- Church history.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Membership lists.; Minutes (Records); Programs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1922-1978, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Poor.
  Biography/Profile
  The Correspondence series contains letters mostly connected with building the new church building in the 1920s. There was evidently some confusion on work orders and insurance, as insurance was claimed and multiple letters went back and forth between the contractor and the church correcting various features of the new church building. This series is in poor to average condition.
  - General, 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1939-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1954-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Building and Grounds, 1922-1923 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Building and Grounds, 1923 June-1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Building and Grounds, 1944-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Building and Grounds, 1959-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Legal Documents, 1904-1956; 2
  General condition: Average.
  The Legal Documents series contains various legal forms relating to the buying and selling of church land, building the new 1920s church building, and a 1955 appraisal of the church building. The contracts folder includes contracts on everything from the glass windows to the roof of the new 1920s church building. This series is in average condition.
  - General, 1904-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Appraisal, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Contracts, 1907-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wavers of Liens, 1923 October-November 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wavers of Liens, 1923 November 9-1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Financial Documents, 1912-1985, undated; 3
  This series includes tithes, ledgers, budgets, and other financial materials relating to New Hope Baptist Church. Many of the bills, receipts, and statements pertain to building the 1920s church. This series is in poor to good condition.
  - Taxes, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ledgers, 1944-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tithes, 1951-1952 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tithes, 1952 July-1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Tithes, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tithes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Budget, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Budget, 1976-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1912-1922 July (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1922 August-October (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1922 November-December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1923 January-June (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, 1923 July-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bills, Receipts, Statements, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Literary Productions, 1875-1988, undated; 4
  This series contains broadsides, minutes, essays, programs, art, and directories, scrapbook materials, clippings, books, and other printed materials. The church conference minutes extend almost the entire time New Hope has been in existence. The programs include performances by New Hope’s choirs and orchestra and solo performances by members of New Hope, including a piano recital by Vivienne Malone-Mayes.
  - General, 1929-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Broadsides, 1899-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Essays, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1970-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Books: Deacon’s Board Minutes, 1890-1895 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Books: Church Conference Minutes, 1875-1890 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Books: Church Conference Minutes, 1895-1908 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Books: Church Conference Minutes, 1909-1921 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Books: Church Conference Minutes, 1921-1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Books: Church Conference Minutes, 1951-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Books: Missionary Society Minutes, 1952-1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Books: Baptist Training Union Minutes, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1949-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Books: Membership Directories, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Books: Church Anniversary, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Books: History of New Hope Baptist Church, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Books: New Hope Baptist Church: (1 of 3), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Books: New Hope Baptist Church: (2 of 3), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Books: New Hope Baptist Church: (3 of 3), 1952 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Books: Pioneer Day, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Books: Women’s Missionary Society, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Historical Notes”, 1945-1977 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Scrapbook”: Loose Materials: (1 of 6), 1925-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Scrapbook”: Loose Materials: (2 of 6), 1925-1985 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Scrapbook”: Loose Materials: (3 of 6), 1925-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Scrapbook”: Loose Materials: (4 of 6), 1925-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Scrapbook”: Loose Materials: (5 of 6), 1925-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbooks: “New Hope Baptist Church Scrapbook”: Loose Materials: (6 of 6), 1925-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Programs: General, 1936-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Programs: Funeral, A, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Programs: Funeral, B (1 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Programs: Funeral, B (2 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Programs: Funeral, C, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Programs: Funeral, D, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Programs: Funeral, E, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Programs: Funeral, F, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Programs: Funeral, G, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Programs: Funeral, H (1 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Programs: Funeral, H (2 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Programs: Funeral, I-J, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Programs: Funeral, K, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Programs: Funeral, L, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Programs: Funeral, Mc, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Programs: Funeral, M, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Programs: Funeral, N-Q, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Programs: Funeral, R, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Programs: Funeral, S (1 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Programs: Funeral, S (2 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Programs: Funeral, T-V, 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Programs: Funeral, W (1 of 2), 1900-1987 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Programs: Funeral, W (2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Programs: Funeral, X-Z, 1900-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Programs: Revivals, 1979-1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Programs: Organizational Meetings, 1945-1984, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Programs: Church Anniversary, 1952-1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Programs: Church Anniversary, 1984-1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Programs: Sunday Bulletins, 1936-1952 January (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Programs: Sunday Bulletins, 1952 February-1954 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Programs: Sunday Bulletins, 1965-1983 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Programs: Sunday Bulletins, 1984-1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Programs: Musical, 1914-1954 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Programs: Musical, 1959-1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Programs: Musical, 1969-1972 July (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Programs: Musical, 1972 November-1973 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Programs: Musical, 1974-1975 April 18 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Programs: Musical, 1975 April 27-July (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Programs: Musical, 1975 July (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Programs: Musical, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Programs: Musical, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Programs: Musical: (1 of 2), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Programs: Musical: (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Programs: Musical, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Programs: Musical, 1984-1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1926-1985 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Art, undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 1)
- Photographic Materials, 1966-1976, undated; 5; 1 document box and 1 oversized box.
  This series includes pictures of various groups, people, and buildings connected with New Hope Baptist Church. Many of these pictures feature the New Hope choirs and orchestras. Several pictures were taken by noted Waco photographer Fred Gildersleeve. The series is in poor to good condition.
  Electronic Resources
  Collection Files
  - General, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - People, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Church Anniversary, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Church Anniversary, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Historical Marker Dedication, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographic Scrapbook: (1 of 5), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photographic Scrapbook: (2 of 5), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographic Scrapbook: (3 of 5), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photographic Scrapbook: (4 of 5), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Photographic Scrapbook: (5 of 5), 1976 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Organizations, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Mattie Conner, undated (Box [1067] OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Stephen Cobb, undated (Box [1067] OVZ, Folder 7)
  - Organizations: Harmony League, undated (Box [1067] OVZ, Folder 8)
  - Organizations, undated (Box [1067] OVZ, Folder 9)
  - People, undated (Box [1067] OVZ, Folder 10)
  - Charcoal Drawing: New Hope Pastor, undated (Box [1064] OVZ, Folder 6)